We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today I start with my traffic light system
for ranking the relative healthfulness
of Green Light vs. Yellow Light
vs. Red Light foods.
Whenever I'm asked at a lecture
whether some food is healthy or not,
my reply is: "Compared to what?"
For example, are eggs healthy?
Compared to some breakfast
sausage next to it? Yes.
But compared to oatmeal?
Not even close.
Think of it as having $2,000
in your daily calorie bank.
How do you want to spend it?
For the same number of calories, you
can eat 1 Big Mac, 50 strawberries,
or a half a wheelbarrow
full of salad greens.
Now, they don't exactly fill
the same culinary niche;
I mean if you want a burger,
you want a burger.
And I don't expect
quarts of strawberries
to make it onto the Dollar Menu
any time soon, but it's an illustration
of how mountainous a nutrition bang
you can get for the same caloric buck.
Every time we put
somethingin our mouth,
it's a lost opportunity to put something
even healthier in our mouth.
So what are the best foods to eat
and the best foods to avoid?
Here's how I like to think of it.
This is my Traffic Light system
to help quickly identify some
of the healthiest options.
Green means go, yellow means caution,
and red means stop... and think
before you put it into your mouth.
Ideally, on a day-to-day basis
green category foods should be maximized,
yellow foods minimized, and
red category foods avoided.
As far as I can figure, the best available
balance of evidence suggests
the healthiest diet is
one that maximizes
the intake of fruits, vegetables,
legumes (which are beans, split
peas, chickpeas, and lentils),
whole grains, nuts and seeds,
mushrooms, herbs and spices.
Basically, real food that
grows out of the ground;
these are our healthiest choices.
In general, the more
whole plant foods
and the fewer processed
and animal foods, the better.
So more green light foods
and less yellow and red.
Like running red lights
in the real world,
you may be able to get away
with it once in a while,
but I wouldn't recommend
making a habit out of it.
My traffic light model stresses
two important concepts:
plant foods tend to be healthier
than animal foods
in terms of being packed
with protective nutrients
and fewer disease-promoting factors,
and unprocessed foods tend
to be healthier than processed foods.
Is that always true? No.
Am I saying that all plant foods are
better than all animal foods? No.
In fact, the worst thing
on store shelves has been
partially hydrogenated
vegetable shortening.
It's even got vegetable
right in the name!
Even some unprocessed plants such
as blue-green algae can be toxic.
Anyone's who's ever had
a bad case of poison ivy
knows plants don't always
like to be messed with.
In general though, choose plant
foods over animal foods,
and unprocessed over processed.
What do I mean by processed?
The classic example is
the milling of grains
from whole wheat, for
example, to white flour.
Isn't it ironic these are then
called "refined" grains,
a word that means improved
or made more elegant?
The elegance was not
felt by the millions
who died from beriberi
in the 19th century,
a vitamin B deficiency
disease that resulted
from polishing rice
from brown to white.
White rice is now enriched with vitamins
to compensate for the "refinement."
A Nobel Prize was awarded
for the discovery of the cause
of beriberi and its cure:
rice bran, the brown part of rice.
Beriberi can cause damage
to the heart muscle,
resulting in sudden death
from heart failure.
Surely such a thing could
never happen in modern times.
I mean an epidemic
of heart disease
that could be prevented and
cured with a change in diet?
Sometimes though, processing
can make foods healthier.
For example, tomato appears
to be the one common juice
that may actually be healthier
than the whole fruit.
The processing of tomato products
boosts the availability
of the antioxidant red pigment
by as much as five-fold.
Similarly, the removal of fat from
cacao beans to make cocoa powder
improves nutritional profile,
since cocoa butter is one of
the rare saturated plant fats
(along with coconut and palm kernel
oils) that may raise cholesterol.
So for the purposes of
the traffic light model,
I like to think of "unprocessed" as
nothing bad added,
nothing good taken away.
So in the above example, tomato
juice could be thought of
as relatively unprocessed since
even much of the fiber is retained,
unless salt is added, which
would make it a processed food
in my book and bump it
out of the green zone.
Similarly, I would consider
chocolate processed
since they add sugar, but
cocoa powder not.
The limited role I see for yellow
light foods in a healthy diet
is to promote the consumption
of green light foods.
They can be the spoonful of sugar
that makes the medicine go down.
So if the only way I can get a patient
to eat oatmeal in the morning
is to make it creamy with almond milk,
then tell them to add almond milk.
The same could be said
for red light foods.
If the only way you're going
to eat a big salad
is to sprinkle it with Bac-Os,
then sprinkle away.
Bac-Os are what are referred
to ultra-processed foods,
bearing no redeeming nutritional
qualities or resemblance
to anything that grew out of the ground,
and often with added badness.
Bac-Os, for example, have added
trans fats, salt, sugar, and even
Red #40, a food dye that may cause
thousands of thyroid cancers every year.
As a red light food, it
should ideally be avoided,
but if the alternative to your big
spinach salad with Bac-Os is KFC,
then it's better to sprinkle.
The same goes for real bacon bits.
I realize some people have
religious or ethical objections
to even trivial amounts
of animal products.
Growing up Jewish next to the largest
pig factory west of the Mississippi,
I can relate to both sentiments.
But from a human health standpoint,
when it comes to animal products
and processed foods, it's
the overall diet that matters.
For example, without hot sauce
my intake of dark green leafy
vegetables would plummet.
Yeah, I could try making
my own from scratch,
but for the time being the green
ends justify the red means.
On the same note, it's really the
day-to-day stuff that matters most.
It really shouldn't matter what
we eat on special occasions.
Feel free to put edible bacon-flavored
candles on your birthday cake—
I'm not actually making those up.
Though I guess from a
food safety point of view,
a raw cake batter Salmonella infection
could leave you in dire straits.
In general, it's really
your regular routine
that determines your
long-term health.
Our body has a remarkable ability
to recover from sporadic insults,
as long as we're not habitually
poking it with a fork.
That's why from a
medical standpoint
I don't like the terms
vegetarian and vegan
because they are only defined
by what you don't eat.
When I taught at Cornell,
I had vegan students
who appeared to be living
off of French fries and beer.
Vegan, perhaps, but not
terribly health-promoting.
That's why I prefer the term
whole food plant-based nutrition.
In general, the dividing
line between
health-promoting and
disease-promoting foods
may be less plant- versus
animal-sourced foods,
and more whole plant foods
versus most everything else.
The Daily Dozen was first
introduced in How Not to Die.
Rather than being a
meal plan or diet in itself,
the Daily Dozen is to
be used as a checklist
to inspire you to eat the healthiest
of healthy foods in your daily diet.
What did a pilot study on
How Not to Die’s Daily Dozen
and How Not to Diet’s
21 Tweaks find?
In How Not to Die,
I compiled the healthiest
of the so-called
Green Light foods
into my Daily Dozen checklist
and encouraged people
to try to fit them
into their daily routine.
I made it into a free app,
Dr. Greger's Daily Dozen,
available for iPhone
and Android,
so anyone and everyone can try
to check off all the boxes
every day and track
their progress over time.
As the feedback poured in
from millions of people
giving the app a try,
two themes of complaints arose.
The first was
that it was just too much food.
There was no way they could eat
all that food in one day.
In response, I explained
that the Daily Dozen
was aspirational,
something to shoot for,
just a tool to inspire people
to include
some of the healthiest
of healthy foods
into their daily diets.
The vast volume of food
I prescribed was on purpose.
I mean, I was hoping
by encouraging people
to eat so much healthy stuff,
it would naturally crowd out
some of the less-healthy stuff.
After checking off 24 servings
in the Daily Dozen,
there's only so much room left
for a pepperoni pizza.
Ironically, the second
major complaint we got
is that it doesn't have
enough calories.
I had to explain
that the Daily Dozen
just represented the minimum
I encourage people to eat,
not the maximum,
and that, certainly,
training athletes requiring
thousands more calories
would have to eat much more.
This all got me thinking,
though.
Too much food
but too few calories?
Sounds like
the perfect weight-loss diet!
The Daily Dozen is by definition
all Green Light foods,
all whole plant foods,
so that right there
bakes in all 17 ingredients
of the ideal weight-loss diet
I introduced in my book
How Not to Diet.
What about the calorie count?
A systematic review
of successful
weight loss strategies
concluded that given
the metabolic slowing
and increased appetite
that accompanies weight loss,
to achieve
significant weight loss,
calorie counts may need to drop
as low as 1,200 calories a day
for women
and 1,500 calories a day
for men.
And what do you know?
Plug in common foods
into each of the categories,
and the Daily Dozen averages
about 1,200 calories,
with the higher-calorie
food choices
nailing 1,500 calories.
In the second half
of How Not to Diet,
I focus on things
that can further accelerate
the loss of body fat,
regardless of what you eat,
which I encapsulated
in my 21 tweaks.
My free Dr. Greger's
Daily Dozen app
had become so popular
at that point
that I decided to revamp it
with these new features.
Now, if you switch over
to the weight-loss setting,
you can make a game
out of how many
fat-busting boosters
you can squeeze in every day,
along with
your Daily Dozen checkboxes.
Does this actually help people
lose weight, though?
You don't know
until you put it to the test.
As part of a master's thesis
in lifestyle medicine
at the Lithuanian University
of Health Sciences,
a graduate student conducted:
"Weight control
and lifestyle change
using Dr. Michael Greger's
Daily Dozen and 21 Tweaks:
does it really work?
A pilot study."
How cool is that?
A before-and-after study
with no controls,
so it's really
more like a case series
of four men and four women,
on average obese,
who were encouraged
to use the app
and follow the Daily Dozen
and 21 Tweaks for four weeks,
preceded by a prep phase,
which included
educational sessions
and even a cooking class,
then followed up
for a month after the diet.
At the end
of the four-week intervention,
an average weight loss
of about 15 pounds (6.80 kg)
was achieved,
along with a few inches
dropped from the waist.
The two folks with diabetes
lowered their sugars
by about 50 points.
LDL cholesterol dropped
by 35 points.
That's the kind of drop
we'd see
with a first-generation
statin drug.
Three reached their ideal range,
under an LDL of 70.
That's really
the most important thing,
as heart disease is
the leading killer in Lithuania,
as it is in the United States.
And in addition
to physical health,
mental health appears
to improve as well.
A month
after the study was over,
the participants appeared
to be able to retain
enough healthy eating habits
to maintain the weight loss
and improved well-being,
but as they strayed,
their cholesterol
and blood sugars crept back up.
It was so cool to read
all the participants' comments.
They never felt hungry,
their taste buds
started changing,
they even learned
to cook a little oatmeal.
Of course, what they were
really happy about
was losing all that weight
while experiencing
some positive side effects.
Now, obviously
a small, uncontrolled study
is some super weak sauce
evidence,
but what it did show
is that it's possible
to make a lot of diet
and lifestyle changes at once,
and if they're healthy changes,
they may bring
about some healthy effects.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.